A Register of the Jacques Benoist-Méchin Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Trial and imprisonment file, 1935—1954. (Box 18)
  - Correspondence, 1945-1953
    - Brasillach, Robert, 1946 (Folder 18: 7)
    - Garel, Pierre, 1945 (Folder 18: 8)
    - Jouen, René, 1946 (Folder 18: 9)
    - Klein, Walter, 1947 (Folder 18: 10)
  - Legal and police records, 1946-1954 (Folder 18: 11)
  - Medical records, 1946-1951 (Folder 18: 12)
  - Printed matter
    - Monograph, 1947. (Folder 18: 13)
      First edition of Rio (Ralph Soupault), Fresnes
    - Serial issues, 1947. (Folder 18: 14)
      Photostats of pages with articles concerning the trial of Benoist-Méchin
    - Speech introducing Benoist-Méchin to a prison audience, circa 1947 (Folder 18: 15)
  - Reading notes, circa 1946-1947 (Folder 18: 16)
  - Writings by others
    - Anonymous, 1945 (Folder 18: 17)
    - Brasillach, Robert, 1944 (Folder 18: 18)
    - Combelle, Lucien, 1944 (Folder 18: 19)
    - Crouzet, Guy, 1935-1945 (Folder 18: 20)
    - Ducrocq, Pierre, 1944 (Folder 18: 21)
- Middle East and North Africa file, 1956-1979. (Box 19)
  Contains clippings, correspondence, reports, and printed matter, organized by name of country and by physical form thereunder
  - General, 1957-1967 (Folder 19: 1)
  - Algeria, 1957-1979
    - Aide-mémoire and letter sent to Raymond Barre, 1978-1979 (Folder 19: 2)
    - Clippings, 1978 (Folder 19: 3)
    - Correspondence, 1978 (Folder 19: 4)
    - Itineraries, 1978 (Folder 19: 5)
    - Notes, circa 1978 (Folder 19: 6)
    - Reports, 1957 (Folder 19: 7)
  - Egypt, 1956-1971. (Folder 19: 8)
    Printed matter
  - Jordan, 1967. (Folder 19: 9)
  - Libya, 1957-1976
    - Notes and report, 1968-1969 (Folder 19: 10)
    - Printed matter, 1957-1976 (Folder 19: 11)
  - Mauritania, 1971. (Folder 19: 12)
    Itineraries and printed matter
  - Morocco, 1956-1970
    - Aide-mémoire, 1969 (Folder 19: 13)
    - Annexes to declaration of protocol, 1956 (Folder 19: 14)
    - Clippings, 1969-1970 (Folder 19: 15)
    - Letter, 1961 (Folder 19: 16)
    - Notes, 1956-1969 (Folder 19: 17)
    - Postcards, circa 1969 (Folder 19: 18)
    - Report, circa 1969 (Folder 19: 19)
    - Speech, circa 1969 (Folder 19: 20)
    - Transcripts of meetings and telephone conversation, 1969 (Folder 19: 21)
  - Saudi Arabia, circa 1960
    - Clipping, circa 1960 (Folder 19: 22)
    - Postcards, circa 1960 (Folder 19: 23)
  - Tunisia, 1969-1970
    - Clippings, 1969 (Folder 19: 24)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1970
      - Lakhdar, Chedly, 1969-1970 (Folder 19: 25)
      - Lakhdar, Tahar, 1969 (Folder 19: 26)
      - Suarez, George, 1969 (Folder 19: 27)
  - Turkey, circa 1960
    - Clipping, circa 1960 (Folder 19: 28)
    - Notes, circa 1960 (Folder 19: 29)
    - Postcards, circa 1960 (Folder 19: 30)
- Subject file, 1918-1970.
  Contains clippings arranged alphabetically by subject
  - France—History—German occupation, 1940-1945 (Folder 19: 31)
  - Germany—Armed forces, 1946-1947 (Folder 19: 32)
  - Laval, Pierre, 1969 (Folder 19: 33)
  - Napoleon II, 1940-1970 (Folder 19: 34)
  - Pétain, Philippe, 1941-1964 (Folder 19: 35)
  - Unruh, Fritz von, 1911-1925 (Folder 19: 36)
  - Wilson, Woodrow, 1918 (Folder 19: 37)
- Writings by others, 1911-1960. (Box 20)
  Arranged alphabetically by author
  - Aron, Robert, circa 1950 (Folder 20: 1)
  - Bergh, Hendrik van, 1958 (Folder 20: 2)
  - Cressac, Charles de, 1945 (Folder 20: 3)
  - Benani, Ahmed, circa 1960 (Folder 20: 4)
  - Déat, Marcel, 1940. (Folder 20: 5)
    Inscribed to Benoist-Méchin by Déat
  - Fenet, Henri, 1945 (Folder 20: 6)
  - Jacquemin, Paul-Firmin
    - 1940 (Folder 20: 7)
    - 1940-1942 (Folder 20: 8)
    - 1944 (Folder 20: 9)
  - Kaiser, Friedhelm, 1940. (Folder 20: 10)
    Inscribed to Benoist-Méchin by Kaiser
  - Kosarenko-Kosarewytsch, Wasyl, 1951-1954 (Folder 20: 11-13)
  - Nasser, Gamar Abdel, 1960. (Folder 20: 14)
    Inscribed to Benoist-Méchin by Nasser
  - Prade, Georges, 1955. (Folder 20: 15)
    Inscribed to Benoist-Méchin by Prade
  - Unruh, Fritz von. French translations by Benoist-Méchin (Box 21)
    - 1911 (Folder 21: 1-3)
    - 1919 (Folder 21: 4-5)
    - 1921 (Folder 21: 6-8)
    - 1925 (Box-folder 22: 1-2)
- Photographs, 1909-1980.
  Arranged in two series and chronologically thereunder
  - Prints depicting Benoist-Méchin
    - Portrait, circa 1925 (Folder 22: 3)
    - With other French prisoners of war, 1940 (Folder 22: 4)
    - With François Darlan, 1940 (Folder 22: 5)
    - As Vichy minister, 1940-1942 (Folder 22: 6-7)
    - With German officers, as well as Vichy and Nazi officials, 1941-1942 (Folder 22: 8)
    - With unknown Vichy official, circa 1942 (Folder 22: 9)
    - Visiting wounded patients, circa 1942 (Folder 22: 10)
    - With Robert Brasillach, circa 1942 (Folder 22: 11)
    - At a religious ceremony commemorating the Légion des Volontaires Français, circa 1942 (Folder 22: 12)
    - At the funeral of Prince Amédée de Savoie, 1942 March 11 (Folder 22: 13)
    - At the opening of an exhibit of sculpture by Arno Brekker, 1942 May 15 (Folder 22: 14)
    - At his trial, 1947 (Folder 22: 15)
    - In his prison cell, circa 1950 (Folder 22: 16)
    - Portrait, circa 1950 (Folder 22: 17)
    - With Gamal Abdel Nasser, 1957 (Box-folder 23: 1)
    - With King Hassan II of Morocco, circa 1960 (Folder 23: 2)
    - Visiting Greece, circa 1960 (Folder 23: 3)
    - With Dino Buzzati, circa 1960 (Folder 23: 4)
    - Visiting Ankara, Turkey, circa 1960 (Folder 23: 5)
    - With King Faisal of Saudi Arabia, circa 1960 (Folder 23: 6)
    - Portraits, circa 1965 (Folder 23: 7)
    - In Vézelay, France, 1968 May 5 (Folder 23: 8)
    - With Tunisian officials, circa 1969 (Folder 23: 9)
    - With Muamar Khadaffi (Muammar al-Gaddafi), 1969 (Folder 23: 10)
    - With General Hoffmann and Erich von Manstein, circa 1970 (Folder 23: 11)
    - Portrait, circa 1975 (Folder 23: 12)
    - Portrait done for l'Express, circa 1975 (Folder 23: 13)
    - Being interviewed by Italian journalists, circa 1975 (Folder 23: 14)
    - With his mother, circa 1975 (Folder 23: 15)
    - Portrait of bust done by Arno Breker, circa 1980 (Folder 23: 16)
    - With Houari Boumedienne and other Algerian officials, 1976 (Folder 23: 17)
    - With relative, circa 1980 (Folder 23: 18)
  - Other prints, 1909-1976
    - Unknown individual on his deathbed(?), undated (Folder 23: 19)
    - Adolphe and Isabelle Ferrière, circa 1909 (Folder 23: 20)
    - Fritz von Unruh, 1914-1925 (Folder 23: 21)
    - Scenes in Germany, including Trier and Aachen, circa 1920 (Folder 23: 22)
    - Christian Bérard, circa 1922 (Folder 23: 23)
    - Otto von Habsburg, circa 1932 and 1962 (Folder 23: 24)
    - Mass ceremony of German soldiers, Tannenberg, Germany, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 25)
    - Castle in North Africa, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 26)
    - French agricultural workers in a field, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 27)
    - Olympic trials, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 28)
    - French Foreign Legion and colonial troops, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 29)
    - François Darlan, circa 1940 (Folder 23: 30)
    - Reburial of Napoleon II, 1940 December 15 (Folder 23: 31)
    - Pierre Laval, circa 1941 (Folder 23: 32)
    - Returning French prisoners of war, circa 1941 (Folder 23: 33)
    - Prisoners of war, probably French colonial soldiers, circa 1941 (Folder 23: 34)
    - Cover of book by Benoist-Méchin, circa 1941 (Folder 23: 35)
    - Philippe Pétain, 1941-1942 (Folder 23: 36)
    - Palmyra, Syria, 1941-1960 (Folder 23: 37)
    - Portrait of Philippe Pétain, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1941 April 17 (Folder 23: 38)
    - François Darlan being received by German officers and Nazi officials, 1941 May (Folder 23: 39)
    - Portrait of François Darlan, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1941 May 27 (Folder 23: 40)
    - Vichy and German officials at a reception, 1941 June 27 (Folder 23: 41)
    - Portrait of Maxime Weygand, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1941 September 5 (Folder 23: 42)
    - Vichy soldiers or militia, circa 1942 (Box-folder 24: 1)
    - Vichy officials boarding a plane, circa 1942 (Folder 24: 2)
    - Hitler's villa, Berchtesgaden, Germany, circa 1942 (Folder 24: 3)
    - Joseph Darnand, circa 1942 (Folder 24: 4)
    - Journée de la Légion tricolore, Paris, France, 1942 August (Folder 24: 5)
    - Bombed building, circa 1944 (Folder 24: 6)
    - Philippe Henriot on his deathbed, 1944 June 28 (Folder 24: 7)
    - Scenes relating to street battles during the liberation of Paris, 1944 August (Folder 24: 8)
    - Charles de Gaulle, with Free French officials and Allied soldiers, Champs Elysées, Paris, 1944 August (Folder 24: 9)
    - Philippe Pétain at his trial, 1946 (Folder 24: 10)
    - Fresnes prison, circa 1947 (Folder 24: 11)
    - Charles Maurras and Robert Brasillach, 1947 (Folder 24: 12)
    - Henri, comte de Paris, circa 1948 (Folder 24: 13)
    - Scenes of Nuremburg, West Germany, 1950-1960 (Folder 24: 14)
    - King Hussein of Jordan, 1950 (Folder 24: 15)
    - Gamal Abdel Nasser, Saudi Arabia, 1956 September 25 (Folder 24: 16)
    - Portrait of Shukri al-Kuwatli, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1958 (Folder 24: 17)
    - Crowd scenes, possibly relating to a visit by Gamal Abdel Nasser, Damascus, Syria, 1958 (Folder 24: 18)
    - Michihiko Hachiya, 1958-1960 (Folder 24: 19)
    - Gamal Abdel Nasser, circa 1960-1970 (Folder 24: 20)
    - Statue of Kemal Atatürk, Ankara, Turkey, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 21)
    - Gamal Abdel Nasser, Morocco, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 22)
    - Scenes in Syria, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 23)
    - Scenes in Iraq, 1960 (Folder 24: 24)
    - Scenes in Cairo, Egypt, 1960 (Folder 24: 25)
    - Scenes in Persepolis, Iran, 1960 (Folder 24: 26)
    - Scenes in Turkey, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 27)
    - Scenes in Jordan, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 28)
    - Scenes in Lebanon, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 29)
    - Classical temples, Greece, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 30)
    - Scenes in Saudi Arabia, circa 1960 (Folder 24: 31)
    - L'Hotel-Dieu, Beaune, France, circa 1960 (Box-folder 25: 1)
    - Bust of King Hassan II and scenes in Morocco, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 2)
    - Scenes in Mauritania, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 3)
    - Men harvesting grapes, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 4)
    - Mystère 20 jet, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 5)
    - Pearl divers, Persian Gulf, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 6)
    - Scenes in Egypt, circa 1960 (Folder 25: 7)
    - Portrait of Louis-Ferdinand Céline, 1960 (Folder 25: 8)
    - Portrait of King Hussein II of Jordan, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1960 (Folder 25: 9)
    - Reburial of Marshal Lyautey, Invalides, Paris, France, 1961 May 10 (Folder 25: 10)
    - Jean Benvuar, circa 1965 (Folder 25: 11)
    - King Hussein II of Jordan with King Faisal of Saudi Arabia, circa 1965 (Folder 25: 12)
    - King Hassan II of Morocco, circa 1965 (Folder 25: 13)
    - Steelworks, Tunisia, circa 1965 (Folder 25: 14)
    - Scenes relating to attacks by Palestinian commandos, Israel, 1968-1974 (Folder 25: 15)
    - Scenes in Beirut, Lebanon, 1969-1976 (Folder 25: 16)
    - Moroccan horsemen, 1969 (Folder 25: 17)
    - Marcel Schumann and Abdelaziz Bouteflika, Algeria, 1969 October (Folder 25: 18)
    - Muamar Khadaffi (Muammar al-Gaddafi), circa 1970 (Folder 25: 19)
    - Oil industry, Kuweit, circa 1970 (Folder 25: 20)
    - Oil installations, Middle East, circa 1970 (Folder 25: 21)
    - Muamar Khadaffi (Muammar al-Gaddafi), circa 1972 (Folder 25: 22)
    - Houari Boumedienne, King Hassan II of Morocco, and Mokhtar Ould Daddah, summit conference, Agadir, Morocco, 1973 July 23-24 (Folder 25: 23)
    - Portrait of Muamar Khadaffi (Muammar al-Gaddafi), inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1974 (Folder 25: 24)
    - Portrait of Mokhtar Ould Daddah, 1975 December 9 (Folder 25: 25)
    - Portrait of Ismet Inönü and scenes in Turkey, 1976 (Folder 25: 26)
  - Photo albums arranged by Benoist-Méchin, 1957-1976
    - Untitled (Middle East and North Africa), circa 1957-1976 (Folder 25: 27-28)
    - "La route reprend,", 1957-1976 (Box-folder 26: 1-2)
    - "Turquie,", circa 1970 (Folder 26: 3)
    - "Arabie,", circa 1960-1970 (Folder 26: 4-5)
    - "Arabie II,", circa 1960-1970 (Folder 26: 6)
    - "Arabie III,", circa 1960-1970 (Folder 26: 7-8)
    - "Maroc—Voyage,", 1971 (Folder 26: 9-10)
  - Miscellany. Three negatives depicting Joseph Darnand and Pierre Laval, circa 1941 (Folder 26: 11)
- Oversize materials, 1920-1972. (Box 27)
  Includes art works, translation, posters, and memorabilia
  - French translation by Benoist-Méchin of a play by Fritz von Unruh, circa 1920 (Folder 27: 1)
  - Self-portrait by Fritz von Unruh, inscribed to Benoist-Méchin, 1924 (Folder 27: 2)
  - Sketch of a house, undated (Folder 27: 3)
  - Portrait of Benoist-Méchin at his desk, circa 1941 (Folder 27: 4)
  - Reproductions of photographs of Philippe Pétain and François Darlan, circa 1941 (Folder 27: 5-7)
  - Prison duffle bag given to Benoist-Méchin by Charles Maurras, circa 1953 (Folder 27: 8)
  - Posters publicizing lectures and a magazine article by Benoit-Méchin, circa 1960-1972 (Folder 27: 9-11)